A Guide to the Pollock and Janney Families Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8409
Pollock and Janney Families Papers 1872-1914
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8409
213 items
Mrs. Frank Nalle
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Frank Nalle of Leesburg, Virginia, on October 18, 1966.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 213 items, 1872-1914, pertaining to the Pollock and Janney families descended from Elizabeth Gordon (Lee)(1813-? ) and Abraham David Pollock(1807-1890) of " Leeton Forest, " Fauquier County, Virginia.
Early letters, 1872-1884, are chiefly from A. D. Pollock to his daughter, Roberta. The majority of correspondence, 1895-1914, is directed to another daughter, Lily, from family and friends. Correspondents include her brother-in-law, Charles Pollock Janney, married to her sister, Nancy Lee; nephews Abraham David Pollock Janney and John Janney(issue of Charles and Nancy Janney); nephews Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and Matthew Gilmour(issue of Roberta and [Matthew] Gilmour); Georgia L. Robertson; Ann Lee Peyton; and others. The letters cover personal affairs as well as the management of boarding houses in Virginia Beach; and, apple growing, farming, and the management of " Leeton Forest. "
Letters, 1872-1884, from Abraham David Pollock are concerned with religious matters, his ill health, and personal and family affairs. In his letter of November 13, 1872, to his wife, he explains his medical condition as told by Dr. Foster of Clifton, Virginia, and discusses the remedy for curing the skin, "electric bath" and "condensed air bath." Another letter, September 13, n.y., concerning his health, discusses Rockbridge Alum as a health spa, and mentions an anticipated visit from General [ ] Lee and a visit by Mrs. [David Dixon] Porter, Jr. Letters of February 4, 1873 and March 12, 1874 reveal Pollock's preaching involvement, mention their baby's ill health, and discuss news of various persons. The latter discusses his son Charles being offered Jimmy Chilton's place, and possibly the Assistant District Attorney position or Assistant in the Attorney General's Office. A January 10, 1876 letter from Charles Lee Pollock concerns personal and family matters, such as Roberta's engagement to [Matthew] Gilmour and a visit by [Charles Pollock] Janney. A July 14, 1876 letter from A. D. Pollock to Roberta discusses her visit to Scotland and his own trip there thirty-five years ago, and mentions the recovery of litle Charles Janney. In his letter of April 16, 1884, A. D. Pollock discusses visitor Fanny Briggs' activities and his new hired man, George Washington, a brother-in-law of John Fry.
During August and September 1901, Charles Pollock Janney of Leesburg, Virginia, wrote several letters to his wife, Nancy Lee (Pollock) Janney, while she was staying with her sister, Lily Pollock, in Virginia Beach. In his August 8 letter, he addresses her invitation to visit by writing that he may see her "on the rising of the Convention about Thursday -15th" but that his "movements will be governed by developments in my Bath County Case, which is assuming interesting proportions." On August 19, he mentions their son John's trip to Washington, D. C. to see Dr. [ ] Patterson and some insurance prospects, their daughter Lilias, and Bell and Harry. His August 26 letter, written on the letterhead of Garfield Memorial Hospital, Washington, D. C., discusses Ben Fling's son Frank's appendicitis and operation as well as John's interest in new insurance cases. On August 28, he writes to arrange accommodations for Townsend H. Van Devanter and his family in Virginia Beach. On August 29, he writes to Lily concerning her final payment to the Columbian Building and Loan Association for her property in Virginia Beach, and mentioning Van Devanter and his wife and her sister, Mrs. Charles C. Mercer(daughters of George W. Janney). In his September 3 letter, he reveals his decision to decline the candidacy for the State Senate, and mentions his having tea with John Staige Davis(1872-1946). On September 4, he mentions a visit to Virginia Beach by James I. Lippincott. On September 11, he writes an interesting letter on a train leaving Leesburg in which he describes a tour of Washington, D. C.; discusses an explosion at the lime kiln that killed a white man and wounded two black men; being called to Richmond to meet the State Committee; states his reasons for declining the candidacy for the State Senate; and Theodore Roosevelt's lessening prospects for becoming president, and William McKinley's assassination. President McKinley's funeral procession is mentioned in his letter of September 17. In his second letter of September 29, he discusses a land transaction and its possible effect on their own family and " Leeton Forest. "
There are many letters, 1895-1914, to Lily Pollock from family and friends, chiefly concerning personal affairs but also the management of " Leeton Forest. " On October 11, 1895, "Margaret" mentions the death of Walter Harrison and the divorce of Amelie Rives Chaloner(1863-1945). Helen Schaw describes life in Atlantic City, New Jersey on January 10, 1901. J. Harvey Johnson writes from El Paso, Texas, on March 17, 1904, referring to his "series of cross-country horseback rides" out west. Lily owned and managed property at Virginia Beach, which was referred to in Thomas Smith's letter of February 13, 1905; Lucy Pegraim Blow's letter of April 20, 1906; and [Olin O.] Provosty's letter of April 27, 1911. Ann Lee Peyton of Yelverton, Virginia, discourages improvements to " Leeton Forest" (December 8, 1906); and, sends news of securing a helper for Lily competent in sewing, cooking, and housekeeping, by the name of F. May Foote, along with the letter of acceptance from Miss Foote (February 27, 1913). Winfield Scott writes about the operation of a mine in Scottsdale, Arizona on November 24, 1907. There are several letters, April 28-May 15, concerning the death of Lily's sister, Nancy Lee (Pollock) Janney. There are letters concerning the rental of " Leeton Forest, " from John Rutherford who agrees to list the farm, with attached broadside about the property in 1899 (December 7, 1910); and, from F. Scott Carter inquiring about rental and necessary furnishings and repairs (April 25, 1912). A letter, July 11, 1911, from Georgie E. Preston, describes a trip up the Potomac River, to Mount Vernon and Washington, D. C., and on to Terra Alta, West Virginia and Marietta, Ohio, specifically mentioning seeing [Albert Baird] Cummins(1850-1926) and [James Beauchamp] "Champ" Clark(1850-1921) in Washington, D. C. On January 13, 1913, Netta A. Goldsborough writes an interesting letter from Schatzalp, Switzerland, concerning the visit for her daughter's health and describing the village and the activities of "the crowds of pleasure seekers, from all over Europe. .." On April 3, 1914, V. Peyton of Yelverton, Virginia, writes concerning Mr. Norwood's leaving the parish and his replacement, Edmund Lee Woodward(1873-1948), discussing both men and their characters. Woodward became the rector of Grace Church in The Plains, Virginia, from 1914-1921. Miss Peyton also sends her best to [Abraham David] Pollock Gilmour and his fiance, Lucy Evelyn. On November 21, 1914, Ida [Peyton] of Yelverton, Virginia, mentions the Belgium relief and the local activities of Edmund [Lee Woodward]; and, on September 1, n.y., she discusses the accidental death of Taylor Scott. On June 23, n.y., Margaret M. writes a lengthy letter containing news of various persons, and claims "What a weary, painful time these married women have" in response to some of the occurrences about which she writes.
Letters, 1903-1913, from Charles Pollock Janney to Lily Pollock, chiefly concern the management of " Leeton Forest" and financial affairs. There is information on wheat and corn accounts (February 28, 1903 and August 19, 1912), apple orders (August 26 & 29 and September 9, 1912), cattle sales (August 19 and September 4, 1912). Charles gave her financial advice and assistance as evident in letters of July 3, 1907 and May 6, 1912, as well as others. On May 1, 1912, he writes concerning his election by the Presbytery as one of the Commissioners to attend the General Assemby meeting on May 16 in Bristol, Tennessee. In his August 19, 1912 letter, he also mentions his servants, Alice, Myrtle, and "a colored youth named William McKinley. " The deaths of William L. Royal and [William E.] Hatcher(1834-1912) are also mentioned in his letter of August 26, 1912. His June 2, 1913 letter discusses a prosposed sale transaction for " Leeton Forest. "
There are letters, 1903-1913, to Lily from her sister Roberta (Pollock) Gilmour's sons, Matthew, a tuberculosis patient, and Abraham David "Pollock", a pastor. Letters from Matthew deal chiefly with his convalescence after contracting tuberculosis, arriving from Scottsdale, Arizona(April 14, 1903, Silver City, New Mexico(May 24 and July 6, 1903), and Denver, Colorado (August 17, 1903). He writes about his life in Arizona; discusses his trip from Scottsdale, through Phoenix and Tucson, to Silver City; compares Phoenix and Tucson as health resorts; expresses his pleasure with St. Joseph's Sanatorium but not with Silver City; expresses his discouragement over worsening health and bad spells and hopes of improvement in Denver. Letters from Pollock begin after Matthew's death in 1904, and discuss family and religious matters. On September 12, 1904, he expresses his gratitude for her "most loving and self-sacrificing treatment of dear Matt." On December 27, 1906, he discusses his work with the Union Seminary; and, during September-December 1913, he writes while pastor of Purity Presbyterian Church in Chester, South Carolina. During these months, he keeps her apprised of the recovery of their child Monroe after being injured seriously by fire.
There are letters, 1905-1914, to Lily from her sister Nancy Lee (Pollock) Janney's sons, John and Thomas Gordon, mining investors. On July 20, 1905, John writes from Darlington, Idaho, expressing his happiness at having the opportunity to take advantage of the growth of such a young city, and supporting her management of the Twin Falls building. As a mining investor in Salt Lake City, Utah in 1907, John was associated with the Nevada-Phoenix Mining Company and the Pioche--Last Chance Mining Company, and was involved in various business deals. During this period, he discusses possible solutions to her financial problems, opportunities for investing, and a financial proposition (April 27, 1907), and the setting aside of $50,000 worth of Pioche stock for her. A lengthy letter, April 27(-October 4), 1912, from John onboard ship enroute to Paris, France, describes the trip. By 1913, John's business investments failed. On January 12, 1913, he writes about the problems of business enterprise even without outside interference, and also wishes for a satisfactory settlement of our war with Turkey but anticipating a "general European confligration [sic]." On July 3, 1913, John writes a lengthy discussion on his opinion concerning how man is intended to live under God's ordained physical laws and the laws of health, and how he has learned to endure difficult situations and still keep reasonably well. On October 31, 1914, John writes from Twin Falls, Idaho, concerning his farm, stating that profits now go into improvements and that he has gradually built up one of the best ranches in that area. He refers to Twin Falls as the most prosperous city he has been in this year. Letters from Gordon are more concerned with thoughts of their mother (December 29, 1907) and her death (May 7 & 23, 1908). On July 29, 1912, he writes an interesting letter from San Francisco, California, about his impending trip to Yokohama, Japan, Korea, and the Philippines to examine some mining properties. He mentions that he has a letter of introduction addressed to the Bishop of the Philippines, Rev. Charles Henry Brent(1862-1929).
Letters, 1913-1914, to Lily from Georgia L. Robertson of Warrenton, Virginia, concern the latter's management of " Leeton Forest" on behalf of Lily. Relevant topics discussed are the tenant Mr. Fielding, the sale of furniture and other household articles, packing Lily's books, and finances. Georgia also writes once from " Kirkwood, " Atlanta, Georgia, with mention of preacher Morgan Campbell.
There is miscellaneous correspondence, 1895-1908, of the Gilmour and Janney families, which includes additional letters of Matthew Gilmour and John Janney. On July 31, 1902, Matthew writes from Prescott, Arizona, to his father, Matthew Gilmour, concerning his failing health due to consumption and mentioning the various treatments of patients used by different physicians. On August 5, 1903, Matthew writes from Denver, Colorado, to his sister, Bertha, about the area, and mentioning that women are able to vote in Colorado. A letter, April 21, 1906, from John Janney in Twin Falls, Idaho, to his mother, Nancy Lee (Pollock) Janney, mentions "the horrible calamity that has befallen San Francisco. "
Miscellaneous items include an unidentified photograph [probably Lily Pollock], obituaries of Abraham David Pollock, receipts of Lily Pollock and Nancy Lee (Pollock) Janney, and a poem and recipes.
Container List
- Letters from Abraham David Pollock and Charles Lee Pollock to Roberta Pollock and family, 1872-1884
- Letters from Charles Pollock Janney to his wife, Nancy Lee (Pollock) Janney, 1901
- Letters to Lily Pollock, 1895-1914, n.d.; (5 folders)
- Letters to Lily Pollock from Charles Pollock Janney, 1903-1913
- Letters to Lily Pollock from nephews Abraham David Pollock Gilmour and Matthew Gilmour, 1903-1913
- Letters to Lily Pollock from nephews John Janney and Thomas Gordon Janney, 1905-1914
- Letters to Lily Pollock from nephews and nieces, 1908-1914
- Letters to Lily Pollock from Georgia L. Robertson, 1913-1914
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of the Gilmour and Janney Families, 1895-1908
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1890, 1905-1906